Let me begin with a question.
我哋先從一個問題開始
What do you think the world needs most right now?
你認為呢個世界最需要嘅係啲咩呢?
Some of you might say peace, because we keep hearing about wars and conflict.
有啲人可能會話和平,因為而家我哋聽到好多世界有戰爭有衝突嘅消息
Some may say food and resources, because so many people still go hungry.
有啲人可能會話食物同埋資源,因為呢個世界有好多人捱緊餓
But let me make it more personal. What do you need most right now?
Maybe it is something practical, like a better job, a better situation.
Maybe it is something even deeper, like love or a sense of purpose.
We all have our own needs.
大約我都將呢個問題講得更加切身一啲,你而家最需要嘅係啲咩呢?
可能係一啲實際嘅東西,例如係一份更好嘅工作啦,更好嘅處境啦,又或者係一啲
更加深沉嘅嘢
就好似係愛或者生命嘅意義
我哋每個其實我哋都有自己嘅需要
Have you heard of the term "Fur Babies"? Let me share something with you.
大家有冇聽過毛孩呢個字呢?
我同你分享一件事呀
I have one fur baby at my place. According to this picture,
Is a picture from the World Bank data. According to World Bank data,
In 1963, the global average birth rate
was 5.3 children per woman.
趙牧師都有一個毛孩嘅,咁佢就想分享下呢個嘅圖表,就係世界銀行嘅數據
由1963年全球平均嘅生育率係每位女性生5.3個小孩
By 2023, that number had dropped to just 2.2
去到2023年呢個數字已經降到2.2個
And the countries with the lowest birth rate in the world, what are they?
全球生育率最低嘅地區同埋國家係邊啲呢?
China,
中國,香港,澳門,南韓,新加坡,
Many with birth rate below 1.0
That means less than one child per woman
好多地方嘅生育率係低於1.0,即係每個女性生唔到一個小朋友
Fur babies is what happens when people
choose not to have children and instead
raise pets as if they were their own
毛孩就係一個咁嘅背景底下誕生,係人選擇唔去生育,轉移去到養育自己嘅孩子
好似養育個寵物一樣
See, I am not here to say whether that is right or wrong
我唔係喺呢度判斷咁樣做啱定錯
My point is this, the trend reveals something deeper
People have lost hope in the future
我想講嘅係呢個趨勢揭示咗一個更加深層嘅問題
人已經失去咗對未來嘅盼望
People nowadays said, even if a war ends today, another war might start tomorrow
即使今日一場嘅戰爭結束,明日另一場嘅戰爭可能又再開始
Even if the economy recovers, it may not last
即使經濟復甦都好啦,未必持久嘅
People are asking themselves, is there any reason to build a future at all?
人個個都喺度問自己,仲有冇任何理由去到建造一個未來呢?
So let me ask you honestly
所以我直接嘅去到問你
Do you have hope for this world, for yourself, for your own future?
你對呢個世界,對你嘅未來,對你嘅人生仲有冇盼望呢?
I believe what the world lacks most today is not resources, it is hope
我深信呢個世界今日最缺乏嘅其實唔係資源,而係盼望
And perhaps what you lack today is the same
或許你今日所缺乏嘅都正正係呢份盼望
Let's bow and pray
我哋一齊禱告
Lord, we come today carrying different burdens
Disappointment and uncertainty
主啊,我哋今日帶住各自嘅重擔嚟到你跟前,可能我哋有失望有迷惘
And Father, I pray that you give us hope
我求主你畀我哋有盼望
We ask that you meet us here
求主你與我哋相遇
Speak to us, open our heart, and remind us that Father, you are alive and you go before us
向我哋說話,闖開我哋嘅心
提醒我哋你係活著嘅,你行喺我哋嘅前面
In Jesus name, Amen
禱告,奉主名求,Amen
See, today's passage is set in a very narrow window of time
The days after Jesus died and before anyone knew he would come back to life
英文係發生喺一個好短暫嘅時間裏面,係耶穌死咗之後幾日,嗰陣仲未有人知道
佢會復活
The main characters are women who had followed Jesus, and in just a few days, one scene after another
They had let them down, a row of great disappointment
主角係一班跟隨耶穌嘅婦女,短短幾日內呢佢哋一幕接一幕嘅將佢哋帶入深深嘅
失望之路
First of all, they watched Jesus died
Scripture says they stood at a distance and saw everything
首先呢佢哋眼白白嘅望住耶穌死去,聖經話佢哋企喺遠處看見了一切
See, watching any person take their last breath is deeply shaking
Whether it is someone you love or even just a stranger
This woman saw it all
望住任何一個人死,其實都好深深震撼我哋,無論嗰個係你所愛嘅定係一個陌生人
但係婦女係全都親眼目睹
And that same evening, they followed and watched, as his body was laid in the tomb
當日旁晚,佢哋跟隨住耶穌嘅屍體,亦都目睹咗耶穌嘅身體被安放喺墳墓裏
They noticed that the burial had been done without the traditional anointing of spices
佢哋注意到安葬嘅時候,並無按照傳統用香料去到高門呢個遺體
So they went home and prepared the spices themselves, a final act of love
That suddenly feels so close to them
於是佢哋返屋企自己準備咗香料,呢個係佢哋最後一個愛嘅行動
死亡突然變得如此嘅真實,如此嘅靠近
Then early the next morning, before dawn, because they are so desperate
They really want to come to the tomb and find the stone roll away
第二日一早,佢哋天未亮嘅時候,佢哋就好迫切嚟到墓穴,發現石頭已經滾開咗
The body was gone, someone had taken him, they said, and they didn't know where he is
個遺體唔見咗,有人將佢帶走咗,而佢哋唔知道去咗邊度
There is such helplessness in those works
呢個話語裏面藏住好大嘅無力感
They had come to offer one last act of love and couldn't even do that
佢哋本身係嚟獻上最後一個愛嘅行動
但係連呢樣嘢都做唔到
They couldn't say goodbye, this moment they felt utterly helpless, disappointed, maybe even hopeless
佢哋感到完全嘅無助,失望,甚至可能係絕望
Mary stood outside the tomb and wept, so overcome
He bent over
瑪利亞
企喺墓外面去到哭泣,悲痛到佢彎低佢嘅腰
向裏面去到張望
好重要我哋去理解佢呢個動作
She is like this
佢會係咁樣
佢係好似趙牧師咁樣
What I mean is, she was so overcome, she couldn't even stand straight
佢悲痛到彎低身落嚟,企唔直嗰日
Looking into the tomb
佢向個墓穴裏面望
And that image is so clear
呢幅圖畫好清晰, Someone who still cares, still tries, still shows up
But has nothing left to do
係一個仍然好在乎,仍然好嘗試,仍然出現,但係已經一無所有
Bent over with grief
被悲傷壓彎咗佢嘅腰
So I want to ask, when did you last cry?
好想問你上一次喊係幾時呢?
When did you last feel that kind of disappointment or heartbreak?
你上一次感受到嗰種嘅失望心碎係幾時呢?
Maybe you didn't literally cry, but inside you felt it
可能你冇真係喊出嚟,但係心裏面你係確實感受到
I also want to be honest with you
好想同你坦誠嘅分享
My younger son is 10 years old
我嘅細仔今年10歲
And he was born, he had several health challenges
佢出世嘅時候有幾個健康方面嘅問題
One of his eyes had significant farsightedness
其中一隻眼佢有嚴重嘅軟視
The doctor told us that if it didn't improve, he might never be able to drive
醫生話畀我哋聽如果冇改善呢佢可能永遠都唔可以揸車
And in a place like Australia, not being able to drive makes life so complicated
喺澳洲呢個地方唔識揸車呢會令到生活非常嘅困難
He also had a curved spine
佢仲有脊柱側彎
The doctor warned that if it worsened
He would need to wear a rigid
Back brace for 20 hours a day
如果醫生警告話如果惡化嘅話呢佢
要每日去到穿戴一個硬式嘅背架20個鐘
Even while sleeping
瞓覺都唔例外
So my wife Winnie had a friend who is also a pastor's wife
趙牧師嘅太太Winnie有一個朋友都係師母嚟嘅
We met her family in 2014
佢哋2014認識
And at that time she had just had her first child
嗰個時候佢嘅朋友啱啱生咗第一個小朋友
Today in 2026
而家係2026年
She has 10 children
佢有10個小朋友
I saw their family photo on Facebook
我見到喺Facebook見到佢哋嘅全家福
When they go out, they need a minivan
佢哋出去旅行嘅時候要租架van仔
I saw how they are going to have their own dinner
見到佢哋食飯要點樣食
They have so many pots of pasta on the desk
佢哋煮意粉要煮好多盤
See I admire her
好欣賞佢
Not because she had 10 children
唔係因為佢呀10個小朋友
But because all 10 are healthy
因為10個小朋友都健健康康
See I know what it is to sit in a doctor's office
With that fear
我好清楚知道坐喺真係診室裏面嗰個心懷恐懼嘅感覺
Every appointment
Every diagnosis carry weight
每次嘅預約每次嘅診斷都有佢嘅重量
So when we look at this woman's experience over these few days
所以當我哋望見呢幾位嘅婦女短短幾日裏面所經歷嘅
Don't we see something similar
我哋會唔會見到一啲我哋都覺得好熟悉嘅嘢呢
Losing someone you love
失去你所愛嘅人
You are trying your best
你盡力而為啦
Things always go unexpectedly wrong
但係事情總係出乎意料嘅出差錯
And finally you are still standing
最後你仲企喺度嘅
You are still trying
你仲係努力緊嘅
But you are barely holding it all together
但係你係好勉強嘅撐住自己
There is a pattern in the text worth noticing
呢段經文裏面有一個好值得留意嘅規律
The word soul keeps appearing
看見呢個字不斷嘅出現
They saw Jesus died
They saw how he was buried
They saw the tomb
They saw the stone had been moved
They saw the body was gone
佢哋見到耶穌死去見到佢哋點樣被安葬呀見到呢個墓穴
見到石頭被移開佢見到遺體唔見咗
But they could not see the future they could not see hope
但係佢哋見唔到嘅係未來
見唔到嘅係盼望
Disappointment
失望
Is
Not being able
To see what you hope to see
係見唔到你好盼望見到嘅
Despair
Is not being able to see
Anything at all
絕望就係乜嘢都見唔到
And only God
Can open our eyes
To see hope
唯有上帝可以開啟我哋嘅眼讓我哋見到盼望
See we all know that God is love
我哋都好明白上帝係愛嘅
And God does not leave
The people he loves stuck in disappointment and despair without doing something about it
但上帝都唔會讓佢所愛嘅人陷喺失望絕望裏面去到袖手旁觀
But the trouble is we so often place our hope in things of this world
但問題在於其實我哋係時常將盼望寄託喺呢個世界嘅事物上
Thinking they will secure a better future
但我哋以為呢啲事物可以保障一個更好嘅明天
But real hope can only be found in Jesus who is leaving and return to us
但係真正嘅盼望只能夠喺耶穌嘅身上搵到
佢活著嘅並且喺我哋中間
Look at what happens
我哋睇下跟住發生咩事
The woman stand at the tomb weeping helpless and then
The angel speaks
婦女們企喺嘅墓旁
哭泣無助
就喺呢個時候一位天使開口講嘢
See I want to highlight a few words in this passage
我想喺呢段經文裏面標註幾個嘅詞語
If you have had the text in front of you, if you have a Bible, you want to highlight this as well
如果你手上有經文聖經嘅不妨都將佢哋畫出嚟
The first word is afraid
第一個字係懼怕
The angel says do not be afraid
天使話唔好懼怕
Why are the women afraid?
佢哋點解驚呢?
Jesus coming back to life brings
Peace, shouldn't them be overjoyed?
係耶穌復活帶嚟平安㗎嘛,佢哋起唔係應該欣喜若狂咩?
If
Out of all the sudden, an angel suddenly appeared to anyone
當然啦,突然出現啲天使可能會嚇親人嘅
But at a deeper level, they were afraid because they never expected God to work in this way
但更深嘅層面,佢哋驚係因為佢哋從未預料到上帝會用呢一種嘅方式
去到行事
God's hope
Doesn't always arrive in the way we expect
上帝嘅盼望
並唔總係以我哋所預期嘅方式去到降臨
Sometimes it
Surpasses what we imagined
有時佢遠超我哋所能夠想像
That kind of surprise can be unsettling
But it is always a good kind
呢種嘅驚喜可能係令人措手不及
但佢總係令到呢一種嘅
呢種嘅美好
係美好的措手不及
Second word, the angel said
I know
第二個字係我知道
I know you are looking for Jesus
天使話我知道你哋係想搵耶穌呀
When we are afraid, when we are lost
When we don't know what to do, God said
I know
當我哋懼怕,當我哋迷失,當我哋不知所措嘅時候
上帝話我
知道
I know what you have been searching
我知道你一路都搵緊啲乜
I know you couldn't find what you were looking for
但我知道你搵唔到你想搵嘅
I know your feelings
我知道你嘅感受
Even the ones you can't put into work
即使你講唔出嘅感受我都知
So you don't need to be afraid
所以你唔使懼怕
What a comfort because God knows
呢個係何等嘅安慰
The third phrase
第三個詞
He is going ahead of you
他在你門以先往那裡去
Before
The disciples
Knew Jesus was alive
Before
The woman
Found the tomb empty
喺門徒知道耶穌復活之前
喺婦女們搵到呢個空墳墓之前
God had already
Acted
He was already ahead
Of them
He goes
Before us
原來上帝已經行動
佢已經走喺呢班婦女嘅前面
神係走喺我哋嘅前面
The fourth word
Joy
第四個詞
大喜樂
The woman ran from the tomb with fear and great joy
婦女們帶住恐懼同埋大大嘅喜樂
Just a moment ago
They were weeping
Not knowing which way
To turn, now they were running with great joy
前一刻佢哋先係喺度哭泣,唔知去邊好,但而家佢哋就係帶住大大嘅喜樂去到奔跑
See, hope doesn't
Doesn't make you say, oh well, maybe
Perhaps things
Will work out
Probably it may work
I'm not so sure
Hope isn't a wishful thinking
Hope brings certainty, hope doesn't make you joyful because you might receive something
Hope makes you joyful because you have already received it
盼望帶嚟確信
盼望使你喜樂唔係因為你可能得到啲咩,而係因為你已經得到啲乜嘢
Hope makes you joyful because you have already received it
盼望帶嚟確信,盼望使你喜樂唔係因為你可能得到啲咩,而係因為你已經
得到咗
Weeping is the expression
Of disappointment, joy is the expression of hope
哭泣係失望嘅表達
而喜樂就係盼望嘅表達
When did you last feel that kind of joy
你上次感受到呢種嘅喜樂係幾時呢
I want to share a miracle that happened recently
我想分享一個我最近發生嘅神蹟
A month ago
At a CNMA pastor's gathering
I had to leave early to take my son to see the eye doctor
喺一個月前喺宣道會一次嘅牧者嘅聚會上面呢我需要提前離開帶我個仔去睇眼科
And before I left, someone suggested the pastor pray for him
喺我離開之前呢有人就建議牧者一班嘅牧者為我個仔去到禱告
Since he wasn't there, I became his stand-in convoy
Someone
Lay hands on me and pray for him
因為我個仔唔在場啦我就成為咗佢嘅替代品
大家都將手按喺我嘅身上面但係為佢祈禱
I am usually the one laying hands and pray for others
我通常係嗰個按手為其他人禱告嘅人
I can't remember the last time anyone lay hands on me
Apart from my ordination
我已經唔係好記得上一次有人為我按手禱告係幾時呢除咗我個案立典禮
所以大家為佢祈禱多啲
所以有人為我祈禱嘅時候我好感動
My wife took my son to the doctor that afternoon
當日下午我嘅太太帶仔去睇醫生
Afterward she told me
之後佢就同我講
The doctor said a lot of medical terms I didn't fully understand
醫生講咗我好多唔明嘅醫學術語
But the conclusion was
最重要嘅結論係咩呢
He can try going without glasses entirely
佢可以嘗試完全唔戴眼鏡
Treat him like a normal person
就好似對咗一個正常人一樣
See, even as a pastor, I feel helpless sometimes
即使身為牧師其實我有時都感到無助
Every doctor's wishes carries fear
每次看診都帶住恐懼
But God already knew
但上帝早已經知道
And he had already gone ahead to prepare the way
佢已經喺前面預備好道路
That is why we can place our hope
In Jesus
And find joy
In that hope
呢個就係點解我哋可以將盼望寄託喺耶穌身上
並且喺個盼望裏面
搵到喜樂
Hope
Is never
Something you can hold in your hand
Or see with your own eyes
盼望唔係我哋能夠握喺手裏面或者用眼睛真係睇到嘅
And it is not
Found in anything in this world that has no life in it
佢唔存在於呢個世界上面任何冇生命嘅事物當中
And because Jesus is living
Hope is not just a feeling
It is a fact
It came back to life
因為耶穌活著盼望唔係一種嘅感覺
佢係一個嘅事實
佢係從死裏面復活咗
He has overcome death
And nothing will overcome it
Again
And Jesus is alive forever
佢已經勝過咗死亡本身
冇任何嘢能夠再勝過佢
耶穌係永遠活著
No matter how disappointed you are today no matter how hopeless this
Things you feel
You are not left with nothing
無論今日你有幾咁嘅失望
無論事情睇起嚟有幾咁嘅絕望你唔係一無所有
Remember this
Jesus Christ is alive
You have him and you have hope
請記住一樣嘢耶穌基督係活著嘅
你有佢
你就有盼望
And the last section of our passage reveals the heart of Jesus toward people
最後呢段經文嘅一部分揭示咗耶穌對人嘅心意
The text says
Statini
Jesus
Meet them
經文話忽然耶穌遇見他們
It reads like a coincidence
讀起上嚟好似係一個即係偶然咁樣
But it wasn't
但係唔係偶然
Statini is the woman's experience
They didn't see it coming
忽然係講緊婦女們嘅感受呀佢哋估唔到呀
But for Jesus
There was nothing sudden about it
He had intentionally gone to meet them
但係對耶穌嚟講根本唔係乜嘢嘅忽然
佢係有意去到搵佢哋嘅
Think about this when did you last
Visit someone
Without telling that person
諗下你上一次特登拜訪某一個人而對方唔知情嘅時候係幾時呢
And Jesus did it the one who created the heaven and earth
Who holds the universe together
And he deliberately went to meet a small group of
Grieving women
但耶穌就係咁樣做嗰位創天造地托住宇宙嘅主
佢特登去一班傷心嘅婦女搵佢哋去到相遇
And that is love he does it for you
呢個就係愛
佢都同樣去到搵我哋
Then the text said Jesus spoke to them
然後經文話耶穌對佢哋說話
We read God said and Jesus said so often in the Bible
但我哋時常喺經文聖經裏面讀到下上帝話或者耶穌話
We always want to skip them
Sounds like nothing
Particularly special
我哋讀聖經嘅時候讀到係好容易輕輕帶過
But we better to pause here
但係我哋停一停諗一諗
If Jesus personally
Speak to you right now would you still take that for granted
如果耶穌親自而家對你說話你仲會唔會當呢樣嘢係理所當然
See Jesus could have sent an other angel
Or speak to them in a dream
耶穌可以差一位天使或者夢裏面同佢哋講呀
But he chose to come in person and speak directly and to be pleasant
但係佢選擇親身嘅嚟到直接嘅講嘢親身嘅同在
This is how much
He values us
呢個就係佢幾咁嘅看中你
This is the depth of his love
呢個就係佢愛嘅深度
And what is his very first word
而耶穌講嘅第一個字係咩字呀
It is an original Greek
呢個係一個希臘嘅原文字
Can we say it together
我哋一齊讀好嗎
Do you know what is Karate
大家知唔知咩叫Karate呀
You know Karate right? It sounds like Karate
聽落去好似跆拳道呀
It is Karate
係Karate呀
So if you remember Karate you remember Karate sounds like the first word Jesus speak to this woman
所以你記得空手道就記得呢個Karate
所以希望大家都記得呢個Karate
It was a common greeting of that time like hello or how are you
呢個就係昔日嘅時候常用嘅問候語好似你好呀你點呀咁樣
May you be well, may you be happy, may you be blessed
大意思係願你平安願你喜樂願你蒙福
It is what you say when you genuinely want someone to be okay
呢個係你真心希望一個人一切安好嘅時候所講嘅一句說話
The very first word
The very first thing Jesus said
To this woman
After returning was
耶穌復活之後對婦女們講嘅第一句嘅說話就係
I want you to be well
I want you to be happy
I want you to be blessed
我希望你平安
我希望你喜樂
我希望你蒙福
呢個就係耶穌對你對我嘅心意
當盼望返嚟嘅時候而佢一定確實會返嚟佢唔係淨淨你返嚟
佢係完全嘅帶住生命嘅返嚟就係嗰個活著嘅耶穌基督嘅身上返嚟
And if you need hope today I invite you to turn forward
Turn to Jesus
無論你今日係咪已經認識咗耶穌或者摸索緊佢係邊個都邀請你轉向耶穌
Not a concept, not a religion, but a living person who goes ahead of you
唔係一個概念唔係一個宗教而係一個活生生嘅人
He knows your pain
佢知道你面對嘅痛苦
And he wants to meet you where you are right now
佢想喺你所在嘅地方同你去到相遇
有一首詩歌講得好靚嘅
因他活著我能面對明天
因他活著不再懼怕
我心知道他掌管明天
生命充滿了盼望只因他活著
當盼望返嚟嘅時候
It has a name
佢有個名㗎
His name is Jesus Christ
佢個名係耶穌基督
Let's bow and pray
我哋一齊低頭
Jesus thank you for reminding us that hope is not a wishful thinking
It is a living certainty
耶穌多謝你提醒我哋
盼望原來唔係一廂情願嘅諗法
而係一個活生生嘅確信
Because you are living, as we return to our daily lives, go before us
因為你係活著
當我哋返返去我哋日常嘅生活裏面求你走在我哋嘅前面
In that moment we feel afraid or helpless, help us remember that you already know
And you are already there
喺我哋感到恐懼無助嘅時刻求你幫助我哋記得
你早已經知道並且你已經喺嗰度
May the joy and hope
of Jesus Christ carry us through
In Jesus name
願耶穌基督嘅喜樂盼望
保持我們渡過一切
我們禱告奉主名求
Amen